( Muffled voices )
( Couple arguing )
( Argument heats up )
( Arguing continues )
' Dear God , watch over me as I embark on this next posting .
' Think I 'll have to get up at about six tomorrow .
' The pain in my stomach persists
' and is now further hampered by menstruation .
' I have taken two ibuprofen and Milk of Magnesia .
' Forgive me my impatience
' but I hope you will reveal your plan for me soon .
' I can 't shake the feeling that you must have saved me
' for something greater than this .
' Not that I 'm complaining or anything .
' Amen . '
- Hi . Are you Maud ? - Yes . Hi .
So , I left some notes out on the kitchen table with all her bits .
She has a mate coming over tomorrow .
Try and keep her off the sauce .
Doctor 's just started her on a new course of B12 shots
so she 's having one of those every evening before dinner .
Your bedroom 's upstairs on the left . Her majesty 's in there , having a nap .
How is she ?
Bit of a cunt . Have fun .
( News on radio )
( Maud ) ' Amanda Köhl .
' 49 years old . '
Can you feel that ?
' Stage four lymphoma of the spinal cord . '
( Amanda ) Yep .
Yep , yep .
' I daresay you 'll be seeing this one soon . '
- Feel that ? - Uh-huh .
- We done ? - Mm-hm .
What time would you like dinner ?
Eight o 'clock .
There 's a shopping list on the hall table .
I got it .
( ♪ Al Bowlly singing " Careless " on stereo )
' I looked her up before I came here .
' Dancer , choreographer , minor celebrity .
' As you know , I have little time for creative types
' as they tend to be rather self-involved .
What are you cooking up in there ?
Spaghetti Bolognese and garlic bread .
Splendid .
♪ Are you just careless
♪ As you seem to be
♪ Or do you just care less for me ? ♪
- Is that temperature all right ? - Mm , it 's fine .
( News on radio )
( Amanda ) Hello .
- Who 's your saint ? - Mary Magdalene .
I didn 't know they made necklaces of her .
I ordered it online .
You 're prettier than the last one .
( Phone buzzes )
( ♪ Jazz funk plays on stereo )
( Amanda ) Hey .
What do you think ?
It 's good .
( Knock at door )
- You must be Mary . - No , Maud .
Ah .
Hope we 're not turfing you out .
- No , no . I 'm going to meet a friend . - Good , good .
Cheerio , then .
' I should have told her I 'd be happy just to stay in my room .
' She must be embarrassed . '
- Can you spare some change , please ? - ( Man ) Sorry , mate , I ain 't got nothing .
Fuck off , then .
Excuse me , Miss .
Can you spare some change , please ?
Thank you , love .
Bit , er ... Bit nippy out , innit ?
May God bless you and never waste your pain .
- What ? - Nothing .
( He chuckles )
God bless you too , sweetheart .
( Indistinct background chatter )
' Why would someone like her end up in a town like this ?
' This dump can 't appeal to her any more than it does to me .
( Phone rings )
Hello ?
What 's happened ?
( Man ) Come back to London .
You can 't just lock yourself up here . You should be around people .
( Amanda ) Why the fuck do you care so much all of a sudden ?
( Man ) Don 't be petulant . You 're getting dangerously Norma Desmond .
- ( Amanda ) Oh , fuck you ! - ( Breaking glass )
( Man ) You stupid cow .
- Hello . - ( Mockingly ) Hello !
Sorry to call you back early .
Silly old thing used to knock it back no problem .
Even I couldn 't keep up with her .
( Maud ) Things are different now .
( Man ) Yes .
Yes , of course .
( TV switched off )
Do you , um ... need me to do anything ?
No .
- She 'll be all right ? - Oh , don 't be an idiot , Richard .
Yes , well ... take care of yourself , darling .
( Retches and vomits )
Pompous arsehole .
You should 've seen him way back . He was constantly trying to fuck me .
He has plugs now . Did you see ?
- No . - No .
Well ...
No one sees what they don 't want to .
Stay with me .
I don 't want to be alone .
How long have you been doing this ?
Just over a year .
What were you doing before ?
I worked at St Afra 's hospital .
Horrible place .
Have you seen a lot of death ?
Yes .
What made you leave ?
I don 't know , I just needed a change .
I dunno .
I think I was spread too thin .
And it 's what God wanted .
When he came , everything changed .
So this is a recent conversion ?
When you pray , do you get a response ?
Sometimes he talks .
You hear his voice ?
Most of the time it ...
It 's just like he 's physically ...
in me or around me .
It 's how he guides me .
Like , when he 's pleased , it 's like a ...
a shiver or ...
sometimes it 's like a pulsing .
And it 's all ...
warm and good .
And he 's just there .
Nothing feels real anymore .
Ever since I moved back here ,
I keep thinking about that last moment
and wondering
what it will be like .
What will I be looking at ?
Will there be anyone else there ?
And then what ?
Nothing ?
Tell me I 'm wrong .
There is more .
And not just afterwards .
He 's everywhere .
He sees you .
He won 't let you fall .
My little saviour .
( Gasps )
( Disembodied whisperings )
( Paper ripping )
' Father , thank you . '
And bring your hand to join
your right hand .
And then draw a semi-circle above your head .
' Now , don 't get me wrong , palliative care is noble work .
' But I always knew you had something more planned for me .
' It takes nothing special to mop up after the decrepit and the dying .
' But to save a soul ,
' that 's quite something .
' Your presence graces the air
' and I feel fuller of your love than ever before .
' More than enough to share . '
Oh .
( Knock at the door )
I can see you .
Yes ?
- Cynthia left ? - Yes , I 'm Maud .
- Carol . - It 's too late to be visiting now .
- It ... - She 's expecting me .
She 's sleeping .
( Laughter )
( Weather report on radio )
( Amanda ) Maud ?
Come and join me .
( Radio ) ' He ended his life last month
' at a legalised euthanasia clinic in Switzerland .
' John said it was his final wish to have a peaceful , pain-free death
' with his family by his side . '
( Male reporter ) ' Thanks , Julia .
' Before he passed , John wrote an open letter to MPs here in England .
- ' He wanted everybody to know ... ' - ( Switches radio off )
Dear God , here is Amanda .
Well , you know that .
Thank you for bringing us together , Lord .
And thank you for this meal which we gratefully receive .
Bless Amanda 's body
which is hurting now
but has done so many wonderful things .
And bless her mind ,
which is shrouded in darkness ,
and reach out to her like you did to me .
Amen .
He 's here ?
I feel it too .
( ♪ Irish lullaby sung by Ruby Murray plays )
♪ Too-ra-loo-ra-loo-ral
♪ Too-ra-loo-ra-li ... ♪
You look beautiful .
- No ! - Yes .
♪ Now , don 't you cry ... ♪
( Lullaby fades )
Hey .
No , I can 't tonight .
You know where I am .
She 's all right .
Bit weird but ...
( Laughing ) Shh . I gotta go .
Yeah , OK . Bye , bye .
Maud , your face .
( Fridge door opening , bottles rattling )
( Fridge door closing , foil ripping )
( Foil thrown on floor )
( Carol giggles )
Oh , shit .
Fuck , it 's all over her dressing gown .
Shit .
Maud , I can do it .
- Don 't let her drink too much . - Don 't worry , it 's mostly for me .
( Amanda ) Honey , come back to me .
( Door closing )
' Religious themes would play a prominent role
' throughout Blake 's career ,
' namely a rejection of organised religion ,
' which he claimed was an ugly distortion of a true spiritual life . '
Hm .
( ♪ Rock music plays on stereo )
( Muffled voices )
( Laughter )
( Carol ) Bye .
Carol ?
Hey .
I need to talk to you .
Yeah ?
- What 's up ? - I want you to stop seeing Amanda .
- Huh ? - Just leave her alone .
- Did she tell you to come after me ? - No , I 'm telling you .
It 's an important time for her .
She 's got big things to deal with and she needs to be focused .
And I just don 't think you can fit into that anymore .
I don 't know what you 're talking about , but ...
I 'm sure your patient 's sex life is none of your business .
I know she 's giving you money .
Again , none of your fucking business .
Look , I 'm trying to be respectful .
I didn 't swear at you or anything .
I just ...
- I just don 't think it 's a good idea . - Please . Respectful ?
You just don 't like that she fucks women .
You could have an eight-inch cock for all I care .
I 'd still be telling you this after the way you looked at her .
- Whoa . What ? - What was that , by the way ?
Do you think you 're too good for her ? Do you think this is a joke ?
- Of course not . - Amanda is dying .
I have a responsibility to look after her .
This is life and death .
It 's spiritual , on another level .
No hard feelings . I 'm sure you 're great in bed .
But you 're just a waste of her time at the moment .
Can you hear yourself ?
Maud , you 're her nurse .
She doesn 't want you to see it but she is vulnerable right now .
And it is not right that she spends her last days
getting worked up about a silly girl who doesn 't care about her .
- I care about her . - Not enough .
- What are you doing ? - I 'm leaving .
Oh .
OK , so you 'll do it ?
Anything you say , Maud .
Don 't tell her I told you , though .
Just , you know , make something up .
Don 't hurt her feelings .
OK .
' I think it went well .
' A whole day and her phone has been silent .
' It must be a relief to her too .
' She radiates peace ,
' and I am reminded of myself in the first flushes of your love . '
( Indistinct )
' We don 't need anyone else . '
Katie ?
Katie !
Katie , hey ! I thought that was you .
How 's it going ? It 's been ages .
Yeah , good .
How are you , Joy ?
Yeah , not bad , not bad . You know , knackered .
Got patients sleeping in corridors .
Surgeries all double-booked . It 's a total madhouse .
So , how 's it going ? Are you taking care of yourself ?
Yeah .
We all thought you must 've left town .
No one sees you out and about anymore .
- I 've been around . - Oh , yeah ?
- What are you up to ? - I 'm a private carer .
You 're still nursing ?
- What ? - Nothing .
Just surprised . I mean ...
- Where are you doing it ? Who with ? - A private agency .
- And they know what happened ? - Yes .
Well , I 've got to go . It was nice to see you , Joy .
Katie .
Take my number , yeah ?
What ?
If you ever want to talk or get a drink or ... anything .
That one there .
Yes , and then that one .
Uh , you can 't do that .
What ?
You ... you slipped those cards in .
Did I ?
It 's no fun if you cheat .
Which one was it ? Hm , that one .
( Phone buzzes )
Can you give me a moment ?
- Uh , yes . - And take that away .
- Ooh , can I have a cup of tea ? - Of course .
Hello .
I didn 't expect to hear from you .
What do you mean ?
Why ?
There you go .
You know , I 've been thinking , it might be nice to go out sometime ,
to the theatre or something .
I would have no clue what to see but I 'm sure you can suggest something .
- And maybe after I leave ... - I want to go to bed .
It 's five o 'clock .
I will go to bed when I damn well like .
Yes , of course .
Now is not the time .
( Lipstick promotion on shopping channel )
( Disembodied whispering )
( Squeals )
( Amanda chuckles )
I need you to go into town .
Yeah ?
To pick up some things for tonight . I 'll make a list .
OK , no problem .
( ♪ Chatter drowned out by rock music )
Oh , yes !
( ♪ Music drowns out conversation )
- Is it ready ? - I 'm just lighting the candles .
Plates .
Get the lights .
( ♪ Music stops )
( Everyone gasps )
( All ) ♪ Happy birthday to you
♪ Happy birthday to you
♪ Happy birthday , dear Amanda
♪ Happy birthday to you ♪
( Cheering )
- ( Woman ) Lights . - ( Man ) Make a wish .
( ♪ Music starts playing )
So , Carol , how did you and Mandy meet ?
We met online .
Ah , so now you have a ménage à trois .
Hardly . Maud doesn 't like Carol .
It 's funny , I can 't figure out if she 's a bigot or if she 's just jealous .
She went sneaking behind my back to try to scare Carol away .
To save my soul , if I understand correctly .
Excuse me .
( Amanda ) Don 't run away . I 'm talking to you .
Maud is my saviour , you see .
She 's been looking out for me in more ways than one , but ...
you got a little carried away , didn 't you ?
So , what is it ?
Am I indecent ?
No , you 're lost .
Richard , want to show us some moves ?
( Indistinct )
There 's my little saint .
( Laughter )
Oh , no , no . Sweetheart , no , no , no .
You know you shouldn 't take anything I say seriously .
I just wanna see you loosen up .
You are a beautiful young woman ,
and you should have some fun while you still can .
I 've got more important things on my mind .
Oh , yes , of course .
How could mere human frivolity possibly compete
with the heavenly Father 's warm heart pulsing ...
Let 's go . Let 's go .
( Groans )
Maybe if you just let me talk to her .
( Agency woman ) No , absolutely not .
You should be thankful she isn 't pressing charges .
Ms Köhl expressed some other concerns .
Is everything all right ?
I 'm fine .
( Muffled voices and music )
( Baby crying )
( Dog barking )
' God ,
' all I feel of you now is this pain .
' A gnawing burning .
' Maybe it 's ulcers or cancer
' or appendicitis .
' If you 're trying to teach me something ,
' I can 't see what it is .
' Quite frankly it all just seems such a waste .
' I was ready and open and alive
' and this is my reward :
' unemployable ,
' unoccupied .
' Perhaps you weren 't as wise as I thought .
' Perhaps I wasn 't paying enough attention .
' I can 't help but feel an act of spite has occurred .
' If this is how you treat your most loyal subjects
' I shudder to think what awaits those who shun you . '
( Indistinct )
( Disembodied whisperings )
( ♪ Rock music )
( ♪ Music drowns out chatter )
Yes , that 's it .
Yeah , yeah .
Oh , yes . Oh !
- Not yet . - Oh !
Oh , God !
Oh , sorry . Oh .
( ♪ Soulful music )
See you later .
( Indistinct chatter )
( ♪ Upbeat pop music )
Hey , Joy , it 's Katie .
Hey . Yeah , I was just wondering if you wanna go for that drink ,
you know , have that chat and just hang out ,
like you said , to chat .
Cool . Great .
That 's great .
Well , you know , if I 'm honest with you ,
I did think it was kind of weird when I saw you and you suggested it ,
just because you never seemed to like me that much .
No ...
No , no , no , no . I didn 't ... I didn 't mean ...
Don 't be like that .
Well , I 'm just at the Star at the moment with some friends ,
but I think they 're heading off soon but I 'm gonna hang around a bit .
- ( Bang on door ) - ( Girl ) Oh , sorry .
Yeah , of course .
In that case , my apologies .
I 'm being stupid so , uh , bye .
( ♪ Rock music )
( Girl ) Oh , careful .
You owe me a drink .
( Screams )
Is everything OK ?
Shh , shh , shh .
Shh , it 's OK . It 's OK .
Shh .
Come on .
- Easy . - No .
Easy !
( Grunting and gasping )
I remember you , you know .
You used to be out all the time .
While back .
I think ...
you and my mate Tommy had it off .
Ah , I remember you .
A lovely , lovely little nursey , hey ?
( Chuckles )
I did everything .
Everything . I changed , didn 't I ?
I thought I did what you told me to do .
( Tearful ) Didn 't I ?
Please .
Please don 't let me fall again .
I 'm begging you .
I 'll do anything .
Please guide me .
( Fireworks going off )
( Gasping )
' Revelation , and just in time .
' Oh , Lord , your mercy knows no bounds .
' For shame that I almost fell so easily . '
( Screams )
' I should have expected resistance .
' Nothing worthwhile comes easily .
' Amanda .
' Amanda , Amanda .
' You called to me , Amanda .
' It was no small thing .
' It meant something .
' Never waste your pain .
( Humming )
( Sighs ) Beautiful .
Mm .
- Do you mind if I sit ? - Hm ? Course not .
Oh , you don 't work at St Afra 's , do you ?
Oh , no , no . I 'm a private carer .
Oh , right .
I have a friend who works at St Afra 's and I wondered if you knew her .
Oh , their uniform is blue .
I honestly have so much respect
for anyone in the medical profession .
Like , any area .
I really think it 's the most important thing
you can do with your life , almost .
Thank you . That 's so sweet .
Yeah , it can be really rewarding .
Not all that glamorous , but yeah .
- I love it . - I bet you get no time for yourself .
Oh , it 's fine . I have my own life .
My own things .
Got choir practice .
This person you 're with at the moment , what 's wrong with them ?
Oh , I 'm
not really supposed to discuss the details .
But you have a good relationship ? You get on with them ?
Mm , really well .
I 'm with a lovely lady at the minute . We 're good pals .
That 's one of the things I love about the job .
You find yourself quickly building these quite meaningful relationships
and , you know , you 're often right there
at a very important time in people 's lives .
Yeah .
Although that sometimes makes things harder in the end .
When you have to leave ?
No , when they die .
I don 't think I 'll be with this one much longer to be honest with you .
Sadly ...
that , as they say ,
is how the cookie crumbles .
Oh , I 'm Esther , by the way . What 's your name ?
' What if I 'm getting it all wrong ?
' What if you are smirking or indifferent
' or think me a clueless idiot like that stupid woman ?
' Is that how Amanda saw me all along ? '
( God , speaking Welsh )
How will I know what to do ?
( Muted )
( Knock at door )
( Knocking )
Katie ?
Katie , it 's Joy .
There you are .
Oh , sorry . Did I get you out of bed ?
- Mind if I come in ? - I 'm busy .
I 'll be quick , I promise . I 'm just on my way to work .
Thanks , love .
Oh .
This is nice .
Cor , you ain 't half tidy , are you ?
I hope you don 't mind . I got your address from work .
Just wanted to see how you are .
Oh , this is cool .
I like all this .
Sorry I couldn 't see you the other night .
I was so shattered , I don 't think I would 've been much fun .
I tried to call but you didn 't pick up .
Want a ciggie ?
How 's work going ?
Are you not with a patient at the moment ?
I 've been feeling bad about the way I reacted last time I saw you .
I 'm sure you 're doing a great job .
You always did .
And I know you put a lot of pressure on yourself .
What happened before , it wasn 't your fault . I know that .
You do too , right ?
What 's going on , Katie ?
Come on , you can tell me .
Look , I know it 's a bit late now , but I wanted to tell you .
We should have been there before it all happened .
We could see you were struggling for a while .
I know it feels like everyone 's in their own little bubble .
But it does help to share .
May the Lord bless and keep you , Joy .
You what ?
It was sweet of you to come but you mustn 't worry .
You 're right , back then I was so lost .
But now I am transformed
and soon everyone will see .
Right . Well , that 's good .
Thank you , Joy . Thank you for coming .
Oh ? Oh , right .
Are you sure you 're OK , then ?
Oh , fuck , I should go , actually .
I 'm gonna come back later , all right ?
All right .
I 'm really glad things are looking up .
See you later .
( Prays indistinctly )
I 'm so sorry .
I was unkind to you .
You made me think of things I didn 't want to .
It 's all right .
- No . - It is , Amanda .
The Lord forgives that which is said in anger .
He knows your heart .
The Lord .
Yes , God .
God sent me to you .
He forgives everything .
You only have to ask .
Heavenly Father ...
- No , no . - Bless this woman in her pain .
No , none of that nonsense .
Amanda ?
( Moans )
( Sighs )
You must be the loneliest girl I 've ever seen .
I 'm here , Amanda .
I am not alone .
And neither are you .
No .
Snap out of it , honey .
He isn 't real .
You must know that .
No .
You felt him too , remember ?
We both did .
No , honey .
I didn 't .
That 's not true .
You have no idea how dull it is to be dying .
I hate to be the one to break it to you but it 's just you and me here .
Nothing you do matters .
( Amanda laughs )
Well , that was easy .
Devil .
( Snarling )
( Amanda as the devil ) Take responsibility for your actions .
You came back here because you are alone .
If you were a true believer , He would be enough
but it 's clear now you are as weak as your faith .
( Gurgles )
( Exhales )
♪ I saw the light
♪ No more ...
♪ I 'm so happy
♪ No sorrow in sight
♪ Praise the Lord
♪ I saw ... ♪
- ( Woman ) Somebody stop her . - ( Man ) Hey , love !
( Overlapping shouts )
- ( Woman ) Oh , my God ! - ( Man ) No , no , no , don 't !
( In Welsh )